John did serve two years in prison and
was released in 2015 he is now a
columnist and author and is an advocate
for whistleblower rights prison reform
and transparency in the government John
thank you so much for coming on how are
you doing doing well things thanks for
having me absolutely so we do know we
have some breaking news kind of
involving jeremy hammond and he is now
being called to testify before a grand
jury investigating WikiLeaks and I do
want you to kind of weigh in with your
thoughts in on this because this is
obviously very problematic so if you
could please go ahead and just address
the you know potential complications
that this adds to the case and your
concerns sure I am very concerned
actually not just for for Julian and the
conduct of this grand jury but also for
jeremy hammond for a number of reasons I
think our viewers will recall that
jeremy hammond is a is a former
Anonymous hacker and whistleblower who
revealed really the scope of private
intelligence in in government one of the
things about Jeremy that I've always
respected so deeply is that he never
ever ratted anybody out he was set up by
the FBI the information is freely
available out there for anybody who
wants to to look for it but he never
testified against anybody he was one of
the the great champions of transparency
in government as you might imagine the
government came down on him like a ton
of bricks and he was convicted of of
computer hacking and sentenced to the
maximum of 10 years in prison 10 years
not in a minimum-security work camp
where he was eligible to serve his
sentence not even in a low-security
prison but in a medium-security prison
which is a real honest-to-god prison
like you see on MSNBC at 11 o'clock on
Saturday nights well Jeremy is nearing
the end of his 10 years his behavior in
prison has been impeccable remarkable he
is due to be released early not just for
good behavior but
also because he's been an active
participant in the our debt program that
is the the the drug drug and alcohol
program that's offered to to prisoners
when you finish this intensive 12 or 18
month program they take a year off of
your prison sentence he's halfway
through it well the government decided
that it needed Jeremy Hammond to testify
before this grand jury in the Eastern
District of Virginia here in Alexandria
the Eastern District is notorious in the
federal system it's known as the
espionage Court it's known as the
espionage court for a couple of reasons
number one most espionage cases are
tried in the Eastern District because
the Eastern District is home to the CIA
to the FBI training center and to the
Pentagon as well as home to hundreds
literally hundreds of defense and
intelligence community contractors
second it's referred to as the espionage
court because no national security
defendant has ever won a case there so
of course that's where they're that's
where they've charged Julian Assange now
far as I'm concerned they are also
subject to see Papa is that correct and
can you explain what that is
yes CIPA is the classified information
Protection Act SIF I was invoked in my
case as well it is such an onerous law
that a defendant literally cannot
receive a fair trial
once CIPA is invoked and let me tell you
the modalities of CIPA - before I finish
with Jeremy when CIPA is invoked the
courtroom is cleared the only people
allowed in the court are the judge the
clerk the bailiff the jury the
prosecutors and the defendant and his
attorney that's it they actually take
duct tape and seal the cracks around the
doors and then they take plastic
sheeting and seal the windows so that
sounds don't accidentally make their way
through the cracks or through the
windows and classified information is
not revealed now for the jury because
the jury is not not cleared for
classified information the government
will insist that any information that is
classified be instead referred to by a
code so let's say if the the term NSA is
considered to be classified it won't be
called NSA in court it'll be called the
swimming pool let's say and so how long
have you worked at the swimming pool
well everybody knows the swimming pool
means NSA but they can't say it now
imagine doing an entire trial that way
where you have hundreds of words or or
hundreds of phrases or ideas or programs
that you're not allowed to utter what
kind of a conclusion is the jury going
to draw the jury is going to say oh my
god if this information is so sensitive
that even we aren't allowed to know what
it is
well this guy must be guilty so this is
what Julian Assange is up against in the
Eastern District well you have now two
witnesses that we know of that have been
called before the grand jury to testify
that will not testify one of them is
Chelsea Manning now Chelsea Manning has
gone back to jail rather than testify
Jeremy Hammond has a history of not
testifying he will likely be held in
contempt
which could then be added consecutively
to the remainder of his term plus one
year for not fulfilling his our debt
obligation the bottom line is this is
onerous it's heavy nothing good can come
of something like this and the fact of
the matter is and I think this is really
the most damaging is that this testimony
is not necessarily in the first place
you know Chelsea Manning's retort upon
being subpoenaed was she had already had
her trial
her trial was on the record all they had
to do was to get the transcript and
enter the transcript into the official
record in the julian assange grand jury
that's it absolutely what they wanted
was to catch her in a lie they were
furious at her that her sentence was
commuted at seven years she was supposed
to be doing 35 and this would give them
the excuse to add five years they're
gonna try to do the same thing to Jeremy
Hammond Oh without a doubt and the the
Jeremy had him and support collective on
Facebook immediately issued this stay on
Twitter issued this statement it says
hello everyone thank you for the
overwhelming support already shown to
Jeremy just as Jeremy had no intention
of cooperating with the government
during his original trial he has no
intention of testifying before this or
any other grand jury he may be called in
front of and the what you said about
Chelsea and in her reasoning may you
have the transcripts from the last time
I was there it they're trying to force
her into a perjury trap they're trying
to force Jeremy Hammond into a perjury
trap and this is basically because
especially in light of the the dnc
lawsuit dismissal where they they have
less of a leg to stand on against Julian
Assange so they're going after anyone
and everyone remotely connected to him
as a means of lashing
hangout that's absolutely correct and
you know I gotta say something too about
about Chelsea Manning Chelsea Manning
looks like uh looks like a small wave
right she's one of the toughest human
beings I've ever encountered in my life
you know how hard prison is he now how
hard it is to be in solitary confinement
it's the United Nations has declared it
a form of torture no yet she chose to go
back rather than twofold there was an
easy way out of this and that was to go
in front of that grand jury and to
answer every question with the words I
don't recall but she didn't do that she
stood up and she told them I'm not gonna
let you push me around and Jeremy
Hammond is doing the same thing I think
that's something to be proud of it's
something to emulate and something to
respect I don't you need to note with
that too as it ties back into the whole
like original theme of the cyberpunk
books which is you can't use force to
solve the math problem of encryption
because a lot of this probably has to do
with the fact that they don't have all
of this information so they don't
they're not able to get it without
having these people actually testify or
put themselves into perjury traps to
then have to to almost lie their way out
of that situation to regain some freedom
so it's the simple fact that they don't
have all of the information they need to
do this prosecution and that's why
they're trying so hard to get other
people involved I think you're probably
right you know in most cases the
government just can't make a case
without having the leverage to squeeze
other witnesses you know they just don't
have all of the information there and
then you know you have this idea hanging
over them that it's not even an idea I
think it's a fact that Julian Assange is
a journalist who is practicing
journalism
he's been awarded journalism awards and
so it's a slippery slope right over the
First Amendment if you're gonna try to
take down a working journalist um they
need the help of people like Chelsea
Manning and and Jeremy Hammond to try to
prove that Julian Assange is not a
journalist and they're not
get it from those two
and interestingly to John is that Julian
status as a journalist actually has no
weight in his case because the US
government doesn't even make a
distinction between who is and who is
not a journalist it's not like a doctor
or a lawyer where there's a government
licensure for that so it's so
interesting and it really shows the
arrogance on behalf of the US government
and it shows the cowardice on behalf of
the major news networks and major news
print outlets as well you're absolutely
right the Supreme Court has never ruled
on who is a journalist and who is not a
journalist there are certainly state
court decisions especially in New York
that have identified for example
bloggers as legitimate journalists but
you're right it's important to note that
there is no government-wide standard
this has not been adjudicated in the
federal system
I think the Chelsea Manning's actions
and now Jeremy Hammonds actions to stand
up this grand jury really do show also
the entirety of WikiLeaks and Julian
Assange and the respect that these
people that whether they are sources or
not or somehow tight the WikiLeaks have
for what WikiLeaks stands for and what
Julian Assange builds I think our media
is spending too much time smearing him
and trying to do a character
assassination and not really tying the
two together that shows how people are
standing up for him I think that's
exactly right and you know I just wish
that we had a way of conveying that to
Julian because by by all accounts he's
really not getting news he really
doesn't know where he stands he'll get
the occasional visitor recently John
Pilger for example and the occasional
letter but I think he really doesn't
fully appreciate the support that he has
out here so this is sort of I don't know
if you could maybe answer this but I
think this will be just very telling and
I kind of think I know what your answer
may be but what is your perspective on
the CIA in general and do you think that
they are or it is a source for a force
for good or bad oh no I don't think it's
been a force for good
in many many years if if it ever was you
know I'm on the record on this I don't
think that there ought to be a CIA I
don't think that in a perfect world
there would be a CIA certainly there are
other organizations in government that
can do what the CIA is supposed to be
doing and that is providing analysis to
policymakers to make the best informed
foreign policy decisions although that's
always been a failure but certainly the
State Department can do the analysis and
the Defense Department can do the
collection and NSA can do the technical
stuff there doesn't need to be a CIA
there was a there was a brief period and
it sound a little naive but I actually
believe it there was a brief period
during the administration where there
was a there was a presidential directive
to respect human rights I was at the CIA
at the time I had been there for several
years and the CIA went through something
called a column C ull where the White
House said if there are any sources that
recruited sources on the CIA payroll who
have human rights problems in their
backgrounds they have to be fired with
that we won't work with people who have
human rights abuses in their pasts and
easily a third of the CIA sources were
were fired they were let go and I
remember not believing it at the time
and then realizing later that no this
was actually serious and the Clinton
people were serious about human rights
and it was applauded by Jimmy Carter at
the time then September 11th happened
and everything went right out the window
you know in my mind September 11th
happened you know day before yesterday
it's amazing to me to think that 18
years have passed next week and so you
know you have to come to the conclusion
that we're never gonna have our
September 10th country back never it's
changed the worse it's never going back
and that's something I think we ought to
all be ashamed of certainly not within
the
duopoly that we have offering is
ostensibly the public relations firm for
an oligarchy no no we don't we're not
going to unring that Bell
you know I challenged I challenged a
democratic member of the Senate
Intelligence Committee about two years
ago I ran into him and I ran to him in
the green room at Fox News and I said
hey senator thanks for all your help
right sarcasm very defensive and he said
look it takes all of my energy just to
not lose my security clearance okay
well that's exactly what the problem is
you yeah because instead of being the
oversight committees which is what
they're supposed to be right this is the
Senate Select Committee on Intelligence
and the house permanent Select Committee
on Intelligence they're not oversight
committees they're cheating committees
and it doesn't matter who the chairman
is and whether the chairman is a
Democrat or a Republican I look at it
this way when we started this torture
program in the first place it was
Democrats heading those two committees
when we approved budgets for a secret
prison system or for international
kidnapping operations called renditions
it was Democrats running those
committees there there's a reason why
instead of of the titles Chairman and
ranking member those committees use the
terms chairman and vice-chairman and
it's because they're the same
there's no ideological difference
between them as a fascinating point it's
it's something that's so often
overlooked especially when there's an
election season and so many different
distractions that can be thrown at us
and I think that it bears repeating
often and I'm glad you challenged a
sitting member of Congress I think more
people should do that either through
phone calls or emails or if you happen
to run into but it just it it
underscores the need for a free press
when people are walking around thinking
that there's an ideological or
fundamental difference between the ars
Andy's on the Senate Intel committee and
there isn't and then you run into the
problem of let's use as an example the
Washington Post which is owned by Jeff
Bezos the founder of Amazon the richest
man in the world and the guy who just
got a four hundred million dollar
contract with the CIA to provide cloud
services so wait a minute is he is he a
proprietor of an independent news outlet
or is he in the pay of the CIA because
you can't be both right well I have you
read the book Fink's know about it's the
the history of CIA influence and
intelligence agency influence and
journalism from like project chaos on
but there's a in an ID you probably can
speak better this to me but there's such
a a a collegial relationship between
influencers and media and influencers in
the intelligence community when it
should be the job of journalists jus you
don't never be at the same dinner party
as these guys for one but to shine a
light on what they're doing not share a
drink or go on a retreat together yeah
and that's not gonna happen you know
when you've got reporters for NBC News
for example sending drafts of their
articles to the CIA's Office of Public
Affairs before they send them to their
own editors for clearance and comment
you know that you have a problem you
have a problem when the CIA tells
journalists you're not gonna write that
story and if you do we'll never
cooperate with you again you know unless
you're Jason Liebman who has the balls
to stand up to people like that you're
gonna end up caving and that's why
that's why we get only puff pieces about
the CIA and what great heroes they are
well in its it's bled into our cinema
and our television since its inception
but was talking about this with a guest
on my show today the the military or
intelligence community influence in
terms of like how movies are scripted
and it's not three guys sitting around
going oh no you've got to change the
shot of that Abrams tank because there's
some specs back there that we don't want
to get out it's I'm sorry this is gonna
have to be removed from the script
absolutely true absolutely true
Joe Weisberg a former colleague of mine
in the CIA's Counterterrorism Center
resigned to move to Hollywood and find
his fortune and he became the creator
and
runner for the show the Americans Joe
submitted every single script the CIA's
publications Review Board for clearance
and every single script came back with
redactions and we're talking about
fiction fiction that was set in the
1970s 1980s and they're still redacting
that stuff is just that's it's
mind-boggling it really is the the links
that the links that people will go to to
prevent us from learning about reclaim
Abul history not even you know history
from hundreds or thousands of years ago
but the history that we were you know
alive for just recently born after it's
all reclaim about history but we have to
hear in an independent media land we not
only counteract the rewriting of recent
history but we have to counter the
rewriting of real time by these guys you
know unless you're one of the swells if
you're one of the in-crowd then you're
going to be okay like four zero dark
thirty right Catholic Kathryn Bigelow
and the writer his name escapes me right
now Mark Boal Kathryn Bigelow and Mark
Boal went to CIA headquarters as honored
guests as VIPs
they were given a bin Laden compound
mark ball was invited to a speech by
director Leon Panetta in the CIA's
auditorium the bubble where where
Panetta revealed the name of the SEAL
Team six operative that killed bin Laden
multiple crimes were committed right but
nobody was ever prosecuted or even
investigated because zero dark thirty
perpetuated the lie that the torture
program led to the to the killing of
Osama bin Laden and so long as these
Hollywood muckety-mucks do the CIA's
bidding they basically have free reign
over the place so I think it's fair to
say to though that the CIA has
definitely infiltrated so much of our
our life in our world they've
infiltrated our academic institutions
and they have you know obviously
infiltrated our you know political
structures and that's sort of thing now
I know that you were you mentioned 9/11
before earlier in the discussion and
that was a pivotal moment for you in
your career
now many people do speculate the truth
of the official narrative that was you
know disseminated to the public on that
day is there a legitimate reason for
people to perhaps question the validity
of that narrative that's a tough one I'm
not a 9/11 truther I was in the building
that day I was I was working on those
issues in the lead-up to 9/11 we knew an
attack was coming we didn't know where
we didn't know when we knew it was in
the offing
so I don't believe that it was the Saudi
royal family the Bush family the Jews
the space aliens I don't believe any of
that stuff but I think the government
has done an absolutely horrible job of
explaining or really failing to explain
for example why building seven went down
there are a lot of unanswered questions
that came even out of the official
account and I think that the
government's response has been just to
remain silent all these years
and hope that these questions just go
away and instead what it's done is to
weaken the official narrative to cause
more and more Americans to question the
government and the investigation of 9/11
and to make the situation worse so yeah
I think the government owes the American
people an explanation John I know you
don't have much time left
I I wanted to touch on an article you
wrote recently in consortium news about
the need for a Russian scalp out of this
this whole two-and-a-half year complete
[__] show but if you want to kind of
give us the rundown of that before you
have to split please door oh sure I
wrote a piece in consortium news about
Marie abou Tina she is the she is the
Russian grad student from American
University who is now in a federal
prison for failing to fill out a form
let me correct myself for conspiring to
fail to fill out a form literally so
this was a prosecution under the fara
Act the the foreign agent Registration
Act and it's a 1938 law that essentially
covers lobbyists and lobbying for
foreign governments if you take money to
act in Washington on behalf of a foreign
government you have to go to the fara
website and fill it out it takes five
minutes you put your name you put the
name of the country that you're
representing and how much money they're
paying you and I used as an example
myself in this article 11 years ago the
government of Abu Dhabi gave me a few
thousand bucks to write for op eds in
support of doing business in Abu Dhabi I
filled out the form I said the Abu Dhabi
Chamber of Commerce gave me two grand to
write these articles I wrote him I was
done so that's all you do is you fill
out a form well the government decided
early on that Maria butanol was a
Russian spy they accused her in the
press repeatedly of being a Russian spy
but they never accused her in court of
being a Russian spy they just leaked it
to the press
let the court of public opinion take
over they also ran an operation against
her there was a guy named Steve burn it
was it Steve burn
what was his first name
Patrick Byrne got it guy named Patrick
Byrne he was the founder and CEO of
overstock.com and and Patrick Byrne
patriotic guy wants to help his country
do the right thing
it turns out he had been an FBI source
on what we don't know
but the FBI approached him and said hey
we want you to get close to this
this Russian grad student Maria booty
naw we think she's a spy so he gets
close to her and he reports back after
several months she's not a spy she's
just a grad student they said not good
enough we need evidence that she's a spy
we want you to have sex with her so he
goes back reestablishes this
relationship it becomes romantic he has
sex with her at the direction of the FBI
and then goes back and says she's really
not a spy she's just a grad student well
that didn't fit their narrative and then
he felt guilty for what he did
later on he went public when I say later
on I mean two weeks ago he went public
but what they did in time to ruin her
was they leaked to the press that she
had been trading sex for access to make
sure I depend like Mitch McConnell and a
bunch of other people do her like whoa
was she was she having an affair with
this guy she happened to be in the same
ballroom with Mitch McConnell and 2,500
other people at some reception at some
point and so all this nonsense that they
leaked at her that they leaked about her
was either made-up or embellished to
make it look like she was some kind of
an espionage mastermind again she wasn't
and when push came to shove not only did
they have to withdraw the the accusation
that she had traded sex for access the
sex was with burn and it was at the
FBI's insistence it wasn't her trading
it they apologized for that but they
never charged her with any crimes
related to espionage or to spine they
didn't even charge her for not
registering they charged her with
conspiring to not register now the
federal guidelines for this so-called
crime are zero to six months in in
prison first time offenders get the zero
she got triple the maximum they gave her
18 months in a woman's prison just to
make an example just to have a scalp I
say this all the time remember this is
how these morons get promoted right you
didn't get promoted by bringing charges
against somebody and then losing and so
they made her an example that's just and
and you close that article with with
with the quote that about your own case
and you've told this story on my show
before but for
for the people that are watching you you
got told by your defense attorney yeah
your problem is you think this is about
justice it's not about justice it's
about mitigating damage yeah I was
charged with five felonies I was facing
45 years in prison I hadn't committed
espionage and they knew it but I was
charged with three counts of espionage
so they offered me 30 month deal I do 23
or I could roll the dice knowing that
the federal government wins ninety eight
point two percent of its cases according
to ProPublica do I roll those dice
I had five kids you know and at the end
of the day when when it was time to fish
or cut bait you know best and final
offer
actually turned it down and I said once
I get before a jury they're gonna
realize how ridiculous this isn't I'm
gonna be acquitted and that's when my
attorney told me you know what your
problem is you think this is about
justice and it's not about justice
it's about mitigating damage espionage
I'm sorry the espionage charges I know
they were eventually dropped correct
that makes no sense to me because you
essentially were giving information to a
media entity not a foreign government in
it as far as I'm concerned with
espionage you have to actually leak the
information to an adversarial government
that's what my attorneys argued as well
and my judge set a precedent in my case
by saying that the Espionage Act should
be read more broadly that a person
should be guilty of espionage if he or
she provides national defense
information to any person not entitled
to receive it never mind the fact that
it is illegal in this country to
classify a crime you are not allowed to
classify information for the purpose of
covering up a crime or preventing
embarrassment and torture was a crime
John Kerry aku any last thoughts
statements that you want to make before
you do head out anything you want to say
about Julian Assange yeah I do thank you
you know we got we've got to keep in the
very front of our minds that this is all
about Julian
Sanj Julian is in for the fight of his
life we thought that the last seven
years were difficult being holed up in
that in that Embassy where he got no
exposure to direct sunlight no decent
food no decent medical care it's worse
now so we've got to pull together we
have to remain firm and tough and United
and we have to watch out for him because
there's nobody else to do it
John thank you so much for coming on and
you are welcome back at any time we
really appreciate your time so much it's
a pleasure good to see all of you good
to see you too thank you thank you